Guide to the Human Rights Watch Records: Helsinki Watch,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Jeri Laber Files
  - Subseries I.1: Country Files
    - USSR
      - Academic freedom
        - Background, 1971-1982, (2 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 2-3)
        - Project, 1977-1985 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      - Alekseyeva, Ludmilla
        - Correspondence, 1979-1985 (Box 42, Folder 5)
        - Projects
          - Proposals, 1984-1985 (Box 42, Folder 6)
          - RFE/RL, 1983-1986 (Box 42, Folder 7)
          - U.S. Broadcasting to the USSR (Box 43)
            - General, 1986-1987 (Box 43, Folder 1)
            - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      - American Bar Association: Legal exchange: Mikhail Lopatin, 1979 (Box 43, Folder 3)
      - American Council of Learned Societies, 1977-1978 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      - Amnesty, Emigrations, 1987 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      - Anti-Semitic cartoons: Judith Vogt (Eli Wiesel, Meron Benvenisti), 1983-1984 (Box 43, Folder 6)
      - Anti-Semitism, 1990 (Box 43, Folder 7)
      - Arbatov, Georgiy, 1981 (Box 43, Folder 8)
      - Armenia, Azerbaijan, 1988-1992 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      - Baltic states
        - General, 1987-1991, (3 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 10-12)
        - General, 1991 (Box 44, Folder 1)
        - Citizenship, 1991-1992 (Box 44, Folder 2)
        - Helsinki Watch: Jonathan Fanton’s trip to the Baltics, 1991 (Box 44, Folder 3)
        - Notes from the August 1989 Baltic/USSR trip, 1989 (Box 44, Folder 4)
        - Helsinki Watch: Report, 1991 (Box 44, Folder 5)
      - Belarus, 1992-1993 (Box 44, Folder 6)
      - Burlatsky, Fyodor
        - Articles, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 44, Folder 8)
        - Meetings
          - General, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 9)
          - Memo on the Paris meeting, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 10)
          - New York, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 11)
          - Notes on Vienna, Paris meetings, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 12)
        - Statement by the Public Commission for International Cooperation on Humanitarian Issues and Human Rights Under the Soviet Committee for European Security and Cooperation, 1988 (Box 44, Folder 13)
      - Center for Democracy in the USSR, 1985-1988 (Box 44, Folder 14)
      - Chalidze, Valery, 1979-1988 (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - Chernobyl
        - General, 1986, 1990-1991, (3 Folders) (Box 45, Folder 2-4)
        - Ecology, 1986 (Box 45, Folder 5)
        - Publications: Foreign Broadcasts Information Service, Newsweek, Nuclear Times, 1986 (Box 45, Folder 6)
      - China repression: Soviet bloc response, 1989 (Box 45, Folder 7)
      - Committee of Concerned Scientists, 1979 (Box 45, Folder 8)
      - Communist Party Conference, 1988 (Box 45, Folder 9)
      - Computer technology (in the Eastern bloc), 1985-1988 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Conference on Dissent in Eastern Europe (Columbia University), 1981 (Box 46, Folder 2)
      - Conference on Soviet-American Exchange and Human Rights
        - General, 1979-1980 (Box 46, Folder 3)
        - Case Studies
          - Berlin, Miriam, 1979-1980 (Box 46, Folder 4)
          - Richardson, Malcolm, 1980 (Box 46, Folder 5)
            [restricted until 2056]
          - Shelanski, Vivien, 1979-1980 (Box 46, Folder 6)
        - Draft, reports, notes, 1980 (Box 46, Folder 7)
        - McKay, Robert: “Some questions…”, 1980 (Box 46, Folder 8)
        - Participants, 1980 (Box 46, Folder 9)
        - Report, other exchanges, 1980-1981 (Box 46, Folder 10)
      - Conference on U.S.-Soviet relations (Chautauqua), 1987 (Box 46, Folder 11)
      - Contacts, 1989-1990 (Box 46, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 46, Folder 13)
      - Coup (August 1991), 1991 (Box 46, Folder 14)
      - Crime and Punishment in the USSR, undated (Box 46, Folder 15)
      - Crimean Tatars
        - General, 1989-1990 (Box 46, Folder 16)
        - Communication: Seytmuratova, Ayshe, 1979-1986, (3 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 1-3)
      - CSCE (Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe)
        - Conference on the Human Dimension, Moscow, 1991 (Box 47, Folder 4)
        - Follow-up Meeting, Vienna, 1985-1987, (2 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 5-6)
        - Follow-up Meeting, Vienna, 1987-1988 (Box 48, Folder 1)
        - Madrid Meeting: NGO material, 1980-1981 (Box 48, Folder 2)
        - Madrid Meeting: Press, 1980 (Box 48, Folder 3)
        - Scientific Forum, Hamburg, 1979-1980 (Box 48, Folder 4)
      - Customs law, 1991 (Box 48, Folder 5)
      - De Burght Conference (on human rights and international cooperation), 1988-1989 (Box 48, Folder 6)
      - Defectors, 1978-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 48, Folder 7-8)
      - Detente (publication), 1985 (Box 49, Folder 1)
      - Disarmament campaigns
        - General, 1983-1984 (Box 49, Folder 2)
        - Publication, 1983-1986, (2 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 3-4)
      - Dissent, 1968-1986 (Box 49, Folder 5)
      - Eastern Europe, 1987-1990 (Box 49, Folder 6)
      - Economy, 1987-1991 (Box 49, Folder 7)
      - Elections--USSR, 1987-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 8-9)
      - Embassy
        - General, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 10)
        - Visas, 1986-1990 (Box 49, Folder 11)
      - Emigration, 1989-1990 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      - Environment, 1990 (Box 49, Folder 13)
      - Estonia
        - General, 1980-1981, (3 Folders) (Box 50, Folder 1-3)
        - Case of Mart Niklus, 1980-1982 (Box 50, Folder 4)
        - Esto America (Publication), 1984 (Box 50, Folder 5)
        - Estonian American National Council: Documents from Estonia (Publication, Vol II.), 1990 (Box 50, Folder 6)
      - Film and television, 1981-1989 (Box 50, Folder 7)
      - Foreign policy, 1988-1990 (Box 50, Folder 8)
      - Former Soviet Union (FSU)--Newly Independent States (NIS)
        - Advocacy, 1993-1994 (Box 50, Folder 9)
        - Citizenship law, 1991 (Box 51, Folder 1)
        - Fanton, Jonathan:The Great Game Revisited-Problems and Potential in Central Asia, 1994 (Box 51, Folder 2)
        - U.S. aid to FSU, 1992-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 51, Folder 3-4)
      - Glasnost and media, 1987-1991 (Box 51, Folder 5)
      - Gorbachev, Mikhail
        - General, 1985-1990 (Box 51, Folder 6)
        - Eastern Europe, 1987 (Box 51, Folder 7)
        - Editorials on Gorbachev’s reforms, 1987-1990 (Box 51, Folder 8)
        - Western Europe, 1987 (Box 51, Folder 9)
      - Graham, Billy: Trip to USSR, 1982 (Box 51, Folder 10)
      - Helsinki Final Act: Fourth anniversary: Soviet and East European press, 1979 (Box 51, Folder 11)
      - Helsinki monitors: First mailing (establishment of HW), 1979 (Box 51, Folder 12)
      - Helsinki Watch
        - 39 Who Believed: Helsinki Monitors in the USSR, 1980 (Box 51, Folder 13)
        - Ten Years After Helsinki: Where are They Now?, 1985 (Box 51, Folder 14)
        - Bernstein, Robert L.
          - Interview (to A Chronicle of Human Rights in the USSR), 1979 (Box 51, Folder 15)
          - Letter to Gorbachev, 1987 (Box 51, Folder 16)
          - Op-Eds (New York Times ), 1979 (Box 51, Folder 17)
          - Statement and tribute (re Yuri Orlov), 1979 (Box 52, Folder 1)
          - Statement at CSCE hearing, 1979 (Box 52, Folder 2)
          - Visa denial--Moscow Book Fair, 1979 (Box 52, Folder 3)
        - Burkhalter, Holly--testimony (Human Rights Subcommittee), 1989 (Box 52, Folder 4)
        - Free Flow of Ideas and People:
          - General, 1978-1980, (2 Folders) (Box 52, Folder 5-6)
          - Brodsky, Joseph, 1979-1981 (Box 52, Folder 7)
          - Distripress, 1979-1980 (Box 52, Folder 8)
          - Druzhnikov, Yuri, 1979-1980 (Box 52, Folder 9)
          - Emigration, 1978-1980 (Box 52, Folder 10)
          - Inkiow, Dimiter, 1979-1980 (Box 52, Folder 11)
          - Journalitsts, 1979 (Box 52, Folder 12)
          - Lehmann, Egbert, 1979-1980 (Box 52, Folder 13)
          - Mailing Project
            - Correspondence, 1977-1986 (Box 52, Folder 14)
            - Mail record, 1979-1980 (Box 52, Folder 15)
            - Postal regulations, 1976-1981 (Box 53, Folder 1)
          - Massie, Suzanne, 1973-1978 (Box 53, Folder 2)
          - RFE/RL (Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty), 1979-1980 (Box 53, Folder 3)
          - Scholars exchange, 1979-1980 (Box 53, Folder 4)
          - Soviet views, 1979 (Box 53, Folder 5)
          - Testimony of Robert L. Bernstein, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 6)
          - VOA (Voice of America), 1978-1980 (Box 53, Folder 7)
        - Joint statement of the Moscow and American Helsinki Watch Groups, 1979 (Box 53, Folder 8)
        - Jurists Committee’s trip, 1988-1989 (Box 53, Folder 9)
        - Laber, Jeri
          - Articles, 1980-1986 (Box 53, Folder 10)
          - Memos (on Eastern Bloc meetings), 1979 (Box 53, Folder 11)
            [restricted until 2055]
          - Testimony (House Subcommittee on Human Rights), 1988 (Box 53, Folder 12)
          - Trip to Strasbourg, 1984 (Box 53, Folder 13)
        - Letters to
          - Abram, Morris D. (on Jewish emigration), 1987-1989 (Box 53, Folder 14)
          - Brezhnev, 1982 (Box 53, Folder 15)
        - News from the USSR, 1987-1990 (Box 53, Folder 16)
        - Proposals
          - On civil society in the USSR, 1988 (Box 53, Folder 17)
          - Expand Helsinki Watch activities, 1991-1992 (Box 54, Folder 1)
        - Subcommittees
          - Eastern Europe and the USSR, 1979-1980 (Box 54, Folder 2)
          - Soviet Union (Lawyers working group), 1988-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 54, Folder 3-4)
        - Testimony and statement (before Democratic Platform Committee), 1980 (Box 54, Folder 5)
        - Vienna Summit: Op-Ed (and letter to Carter), 1979 (Box 54, Folder 6)
      - Human Rights
        - General, 1986-1990 (Box 54, Folder 7)
        - Human Rights Group of Moscow Society ‘Memorial’, 1990 (Box 54, Folder 8)
        - News Briefs, 1988-1989 (Box 54, Folder 9)
        - Human Rights Project Group, 1988-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 54, Folder 10-11)
        - Human Rights Project Group, 1989-1990 (Box 55, Folder 1)
      - International Conference on Collective Phenomena, 1980 (Box 55, Folder 2)
      - International covenants on human rights, 1979-1981 (Box 55, Folder 3)
      - IPSA (International Political Science Association) Conference in Moscow, 1978-1979
        - General, 1978-1979 (Box 55, Folder 4)
        - Publication, 1978-1979 (Box 55, Folder 5)
      - International Postal Communication: CSCE, Madrid, 1980 (Box 55, Folder 6)
      - IREX (International Research and Exchanges Board), 1979 (Box 55, Folder 7)
      - Intra-bloc (Soviet bloc), 1988-1989 (Box 55, Folder 8)
      - Jackson-Vanik overview (Box 55, Folder 9)
      - Juviler, Peter:Human Rights in the USSR: An American View, 1989 (Box 56, Folder 1)
      - Kazakhstan, 1989-1993 (Box 56, Folder 2)
      - KGB files, 1992 (Box 56, Folder 3)
      - Kopelev, Lev and Raya, 1981-1983 (Box 56, Folder 4)
      - Kurds in the Soviet Union, 1987-1990 (Box 56, Folder 5)
      - Latvia
        - General, 1991-1993 (Box 56, Folder 6)
        - Calitis, Ints, undated (Box 56, Folder 7)
        - Citizenship, 1991 (Box 56, Folder 8)
        - Contacts, 1989-1990 (Box 56, Folder 9)
        - Leaders, 1988-1989 (Box 56, Folder 10)
      - Law
        - British commentary (on Soviet criminal procedure), 1983-1984 (Box 56, Folder 11)
        - FBIS (Foreign Broadcasts Information Service)
          - Clippings on legal issues, 1988-1989 (Box 56, Folder 12)
          - Legal systems-Western, 1970 (Box 56, Folder 13)
          - Publication--Digest, 1986 (Box 56, Folder 14)
      - Legal documentation, 1993 (Box 56, Folder 15)
      - Legal reforms, 1990 (Box 56, Folder 16)
      - Legislation
        - New, 1983-1986 (Box 56, Folder 17)
        - New, 1987-1988 (Box 57, Folder 1)
      - Lithuania
        - General, 1980-1986 (Box 57, Folder 2)
        - Contacts, 1989-1991 (Box 57, Folder 3)
        - Elta Information Bulletin (monthly), 1982-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 57, Folder 4-5)
        - Events of January 11-13, 1991
          - Lithuanian procurator’s report, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 6)
          - Shchit-Shield report, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 7)
          - Soviet prosecutor’s report, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 8)
        - Lithuanian Information Center: Press releases, 1982-1984 (Box 57, Folder 9)
        - Medininkai massacre, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 10)
        - Post-January period, 1991-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 57, Folder 11-12)
        - Rehabilitation, 1991-1992 (Box 57, Folder 13)
        - Secret CPSU (Communist Party of the Soviet Union)-memo on Lithuania, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 14)
        - The Baltic Independent (weekly), 1991 (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Marriage by proxy, 1981 (Box 58, Folder 2)
      - Military, 1990-1992 (Box 58, Folder 3)
      - Moldova, 1990-1992 (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Moscow Book Fair
        - General, 1978-1987, (5 Folders) (Box 58, Folder 5-9)
        - Statements
          - Russian, 1981 (Box 58, Folder 10)
          - Moscow Book Fair in Exile, 1981 (Box 58, Folder 11)
        - Moscow human rights conference, 1987-1991 (Box 58, Folder 12)
        - Music, 1982-1989 (Box 58, Folder 13)
        - National Academy of Sciences, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 14)
        - National Endowment for Democracy, 1983-1989 (Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Nationalities
          - General, 1989-1991 (Box 59, Folder 2)
          - The Ex-Soviet Nationalities Without Gorbachev, 1992 (Box 59, Folder 3)
          - Conference on the Major Non-Slavic Nationalities of the USSR, Harvard University, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 4)
      - Non-interference (in the internal affairs of states), undated (Box 59, Folder 5)
      - Orlov, Yuri:
        - Correspondence (re, Orlov), 1987 (Box 59, Folder 6)
        - Defense
        - General, 1978-1980 (Box 59, Folder 7)
        - Reception for J. Macdonald (Orlov’s lawyer), 1978-1979 (Box 59, Folder 8)
        - Memorandum: “The Meaning of Gorbachev's Reforms”, 1988 (Box 59, Folder 9)
        - The Orlov Tribunal (Index on Censorship ), 1977 (Box 59, Folder 10)
        - Poster campaign, 1982-1983 (Box 59, Folder 11)
        - Visa (to IHF Annual Meeting, Moscow), 1990 (Box 59, Folder 12)
      - Party conference, 1988 (Box 59, Folder 13)
      - Past abuses, 1990-1992 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      - Political Prisoner Day, 1979-1979 (Box 60, Folder 2)
      - Political prisoners
        - General, 1987-1990 (Box 60, Folder 3)
        - Campaign on their behalf, 1981 (Box 60, Folder 4)
        - Forgotten Prisoners in Perm Camp, 1987 (Box 60, Folder 5)
        - Kazachkov, Mikhail, 1989-1990 (Box 60, Folder 6)
        - List of Political Prisoners in the USSR, 1986 (Box 60, Folder 7)
        - Prisoners and Camps in the USSR (Orlov), 1979 (Box 60, Folder 8)
        - Releases and continued detention (International Helsinki Federation for Human Rights), 1988 (Box 60, Folder 9)
        - Women Political Prisoners in the USSR, 1975 (Box 60, Folder 10)
      - Politics, 1987-1990 (Box 60, Folder 11)
      - Pravda, 1982 (Box 60, Folder 12)
      - Presidency, 1990 (Box 60, Folder 13)
      - Press Club Glasnost
        - General, 1987 (Box 60, Folder 14)
        - Contributions, 1988 (Box 60, Folder 15)
      - Prisons
        - Appeal to Helsinki Committee: Kovalskaia, G., 1990 (Box 60, Folder 16)
        - Maximova, G.:Chronicle of My Six Years in Prison, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 17)
        - Publications, 1975-1976 (Box 60, Folder 18)
      - Psychiatric abuse
        - General, 1987-1988 (Box 60, Folder 19)
        - Draft report of Moscow Committee for Human Rights coordinator Yuri Chernev, 1990 (Box 60, Folder 20)
        - Geneva Initiative, 1992 (Box 60, Folder 21)
        - Individual cases (Box 61)
          - Dolchuk, A., 1990 (Box 61, Folder 1)
          - Komitskaia, Alla, 1987-1990 (Box 61, Folder 2)
          - Nemirovskaia, Klara, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 3)
          - Olenik, Valentina, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 4)
          - Proshchin, Boris, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 5)
          - Rainov, Viktor, 1983-1990 (Box 61, Folder 6)
          - Rosinskaia, Emma, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 7)
          - Slobodsky, Naum Yosifovich, 1989 (Box 61, Folder 8)
          - Voevodin, Vadim, 1987-1990 (Box 61, Folder 9)
        - Int’l Association on the Political Use of Psychiatry, 1987-1990 (Box 61, Folder 10)
      - Psychiatry
        - Soviet psychiatrists, 1990 (Box 61, Folder 11)
        - World Psychiatric Association
          - General, 1973-1979 (Box 61, Folder 12)
          - Moscow Symposium, 1978-1979 (Box 61, Folder 13)
        - U.S. Delegation to Assess Recent Changes in Soviet Psychiatry-Report, 1989 (Box 61, Folder 14)
      - Reformers, 1988-1989 (Box 61, Folder 15)
      - Reforms, 1988-1989 (Box 62, Folder 1)
      - Refugees, 1988-1990 (Box 62, Folder 2)
      - Repression: Administrative punishment: Budinskaia, Svetlana, 1984-1990 (Box 62, Folder 3)
      - Revelations, rehabilitations, 1987-1989 (Box 62, Folder 4)
      - Rosenthal, A. M.: Articles, 1988 (Box 62, Folder 5)
      - Russian nationalism, 1990 (Box 62, Folder 6)
      - Sakharov, Andrei
        - General, 1979-1984, (3 Folders) (Box 62, Folder 7-9)
        - Defense campaign, 1980 (Box 62, Folder 10)
        - Helsinki Watch statements, undated (Box 62, Folder 11)
        - Hunger strike, 1980-1982 (Box 62, Folder 12)
        - Letter re political prisoners worldwide, undated (Box 63, Folder 1)
        - Meeting, 1980 (Box 63, Folder 2)
        - Obituaries, 1989 (Box 63, Folder 3)
        - Press conference, 1980 (Box 63, Folder 4)
        - Questionnaire, 1977-1980 (Box 63, Folder 5)
        - Sakharov Watch, 1986 (Box 63, Folder 6)
      - S.A.L.T. (Strategic arms limitation treaties) talks, 1979 (Box 63, Folder 7)
      - Scientists
        - General, 1979-1981, (2 Folders) (Box 63, Folder 8-9)
        - AAAS (American Association for the Advancement of Science), 1975-1979 (Box 63, Folder 10)
        - Exchange, 1980-1981 (Box 63, Folder 11)
        - Visa denials to Eastern bloc scientists, 1980 (Box 63, Folder 12)
        - Scientists for Orlov and Sharansky, 1979-1981 (Box 63, Folder 13)
      - Secret police, 1992 (Box 63, Folder 14)
      - Security issues (NATO, military), 1980 (Box 64, Folder 1)
      - Serebrov, Felix, 1981 (Box 64, Folder 2)
      - Shcharansky, Anatoly, undated (Box 64, Folder 3)
      - Shelkov, Vladimir: Call for release, 1979 (Box 64, Folder 4)
      - Slepak principles, 1989 (Box 64, Folder 5)
      - Society: Demography, 1988-1990 (Box 64, Folder 6)
      - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, 1990 (Box 64, Folder 7)
      - Soros Foundation: Newsletter, 1991 (Box 64, Folder 8)
      - Soviet allegations (of U.S. human rights abuses), 1987-1988 (Box 64, Folder 9)
      - Soviet charges of U.S. violations of the Helsinki Accords, 1980 (Box 64, Folder 10)
      - Soviet Jewry
        - General, 1979-1980, 1983-1988, (4 Folders) (Box 64, Folder 11-14)
        - General, 1989-1991, (5 Folders) (Box 65, Folder 1-5)
        - Emigration
          - General, 1980 (Box 65, Folder 6)
          - Tesler, Zhanna, 1989 (Box 65, Folder 7)
        - Greater New York Conference on Soviet Jewry, 1978 (Box 65, Folder 8)
        - New York Legal Coalition for Soviet Jewry
          - Conference material for Madrid, 1979-1980 (Box 65, Folder 9)
          - Refuseniks, 1977 (Box 65, Folder 10)
          - Refuseniks, 1990 (Box 65, Folder 11)
      - Soviet literature, undated (Box 66, Folder 1)
      - Strikes (Summer 1989), 1989 (Box 66, Folder 2)
      - Tajikistan, 1990-1993 (Box 66, Folder 3)
      - Technology, 1988 (Box 66, Folder 4)
      - Telephone links: East (Moscow)--West, 1982-1986 (Box 66, Folder 5)
      - Television, 1986-1988 (Box 66, Folder 6)
      - Theater, 1987-1989 (Box 66, Folder 7)
      - Traveler’s handbook, 1979 (Box 66, Folder 8)
      - Turkmenistan, 1993 (Box 66, Folder 9)
      - Ukraine
        - General, 1983-1993 (Box 66, Folder 10)
        - Zisels, Joseph Samuilevich, 1979-1980 (Box 66, Folder 11)
        - Ukrainian Helsinki Group
          - General, 1974-1984 (Box 66, Folder 12)
          - Sychko, Vasil and Petro: Call for their release, 1979 (Box 66, Folder 13)
          - Ukrainian Helsinki Union, 1988 (Box 66, Folder 14)
      - United States
        - Bush administration, 1988-1990, (2 Folders) (Box 66, Folder 15-16)
        - European Press Guidance, 1989 (Box 67, Folder 1)
        - Bush-Kissinger, 1989 (Box 67, Folder 2)
        - Domestic compliance with Helsinki Accords, 1979-1980 (Box 67, Folder 3)
        - Policy, 1991 (Box 67, Folder 4)
        - Scientific exchange, 1978-1979 (Box 67, Folder 5)
        - State department, 1981 (Box 67, Folder 6)
      - Universal Copyright Convention: “Moscow’s Copyright Maneuver”, 1973 (Box 67, Folder 7)
      - Uzbekistan, 1989-1990 (Box 67, Folder 8)
      - VOA (Voice of America), RFE/RL (Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty), BBC, 1980-1988, (2 Folders) (Box 67, Folder 9-10)
      - Wallenberg, Raoul, 1982 (Box 67, Folder 11)
      - Warnke, Paul, 1982 (Box 67, Folder 12)
      - Watson meeting (Thomas J. Watson, Ambassador to USSR), 1979 (Box 67, Folder 13)
      - Wiseberg, Laurie:Report on the Ninth World Congress of the International Political Science Association, 1979 (Box 67, Folder 14)
      - Writers (and other artists), 1975-1982 (Box 67, Folder 15)
      - Yakovlevich, Lubman Leonid, 1988 (Box 68, Folder 1)
      - Yalta, 1986-1987 (Box 68, Folder 2)
      - Yankelevich, Tanya, 1981 (Box 68, Folder 3)
      - Yarym-Agayev, Yuri, 1979-1987 (Box 68, Folder 4)
      - Youth, 1987 (Box 68, Folder 5)
      - Zagalsky, Leonid (possible consultant), 1991 (Box 68, Folder 6)
      - Zevelev, Igor: (Communist Ideology and human rights), 1992 (Box 68, Folder 7)
      - United States
        - Compliance--with Helsinki Accords--Visa denials, 1987-1988 (Box 68, Folder 8)
        - Department of State
          - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 68, Folder 9)
          - Critique, 1979-1981 (Box 68, Folder 10)
        - Los Angeles police--brutality, 1991 (Box 68, Folder 11)
        - McCarran-Walter Act (immigration), 1990 (Box 68, Folder 12)
        - Native Americans, 1979-1988 (Box 68, Folder 13)
        - Prisoners
          - Bell v. Wolfish, 1979 (Box 68, Folder 14)
          - Conscientious objection, 1991 (Box 68, Folder 15)
          - Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 68, Folder 16)
          - Prisoners Assistance Directory (ACLU), 1981 (Box 68, Folder 17)
          - Prisoners’ rights report, 1979-1981 (Box 68, Folder 18)
        - Reagan administration, 1985 (Box 68, Folder 19)
        - Reagan-Bush Committee, 1980 (Box 68, Folder 20)
        - UN Genocide Convention: Articles, letters, 1984 (Box 68, Folder 21)
      - Yugoslavia
        - General, 1980-1984 (Box 68, Folder 22)
        - General, 1985-1992 (Box 69, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 2)
        - Egyptians, 1990 (Box 69, Folder 3)
        - Émigrés, 1969-1979 (Box 69, Folder 4)
        - Gentile, Louis (Report on United Nations operations in Bosnia), 1994-1995 (Box 69, Folder 5)
        - Helsinki Watch
          - Burkhalter, Holly--testimony, 1992 (Box 69, Folder 6)
          - Fanton, Jonathan: “Yugoslavia revisited”, 1992 (Box 69, Folder 7)
          - J. Laber’s testimonies, 1991-1992 (Box 69, Folder 8)
          - Letter to the President (Dobrica Cosic), 1992 (Box 69, Folder 9)
          - Reports
            - Yugoslavia: Freedom to Conform, 1982 (Box 69, Folder 10)
            - Yugoslavia (Serbia and Montenegro)-Persecution Persists: Human Rights Violations in Kosovo, 1996 (Box 69, Folder 11)
            - Trip to Yugoslavia, 1988 (Box 69, Folder 12)
        - Mihajlov, Mihajlo, 1979-1984 (Box 69, Folder 13)
        - Past abuses, 1990 (Box 69, Folder 14)
        - Popovic, Srdja, 1983 (Box 69, Folder 15)
        - Prisons, 1990 (Box 69, Folder 16)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Czechoslovakia, 1980-1989 (Box 70, Folder 1)